Guide to the George Augustus Sala Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Ralph Straus Papers Relating to George Augustus Sala, 1841-1942; Series I; 10.09; (15 boxes)
  - Writings by George Augustus Sala
    - Other Writings
      - Other writings and fragments, autograph manuscript, 1873-1890, undated; 2 (Box 14)
        "Subjects for pictures" and "Tetzel Spelling Indulgences," notes from a scrapbook, 2 pages, [1873?].
        "Mozart's letters: 1769-1791," notes from a scrapbook, 1 page, [1873?].
        Notes from a scrapbook, 1 page, [1873?].
        Notes from a scrapbook, after his illness, 1 page, [1873?].
        Notes from a scrapbook, 1 page, 1874 January.
        "Cupid," 5 pages. Published in the Gentleman's Magazine, 1878 September and October.
        "The Dogs of Constantinople," 1 page, 1877 January 27.
        "The Didactic Village," 2 pages, [1878 January].
        "The Play House," 1 page 1881 May 14.
        "Echos from a Distance," 2 pages, 1881 September 3.
        "Echos of the Week," fragment, 1 page, 1882 August 26.
        Poem beginning "Maid of Monmouth," 1 page, [copyright 1888].
        Poem sent to H. Stacy Marks in reply to an invitation, 1 page, 1890 October 10.
        Article on the Social Science Congress, notes, 1 page.
        "Echoes of the Week," fragment, 1 page, with note signed by Bessie Stannard Sala.
        "Exhibition of the Royal Academy: Eighth Notice Sculpture," draft, 1 page.
      - Notebook, 1858-1888; 2 (Box 15)
        Contains autograph manuscript notes, and pen-and-ink and pencil sketches.
      - Notebook, 1858-1888; 2 (Box 15)
      - Temple Bar, clippings and related materials, 1860-1862 (Box 15)
        London magazine edited by Sala.
      - "The Topical Times," print, with autograph manuscript notes, circa 1864 (Box 15)
        Caricature representing contemporaries of Sala, with identifying notes by him.
  - Other Papers of George Augustus Sala
    - Facsimiles and clippings pertaining to Sala's writing and illustrations, 1875-1906; 2 (Box 15)
      "Gerald Moreland," 2 sketches.
      Figures and caricatures, 4 sketches.
      Notes and sketches by Watts Phillips, 1 facsimile.
      Sala's handwriting, 1 facsimile.
      4 letters from Sala, facsimile, to: Edward Levy, undated; Figaro, 1875 April 21; John Latey, 1880 December 29; Daily Graphic, 1891 August 19.
      "Bedrooms on Wheels," fragment, facsimile.
      "America Revisited," fragment, facsimile.
      London: A Weekly Journal of Literature, title page, 1 facsimile.
      Sala, Bessie Stannard. Famous People I Have Met (London, 1892), letters, 5 facsimiles.
      "Mr. Punch's Progress," clipping, Pearson's Magazine, 1906 December, pages [629]-640.
      "The Late George Augustus Sala as an Illustrator," clipping, Minster Magazine, 1906 February, 2 pages.
    - Family album, 1840; 2 (Box 15)
      Inscribed: "Augusta Sala. Paris. 1840."
      Contains poems and drawings by members of the Sala family, and possibly others; and pressed flowers gathered at Paris and elsewhere after 1840.
    - Portrait of Sala, oil on wood, undated (Box 15)
      Possibly a self portrait.
    - 2 passports, 1856, 1876 (Box 15)
      Issued to Sala for travel in Europe.
    - Programs, menus, invitations, etc., 1860-1895; 5 (Box 16)
      Includes a card of admission to Robert Browning's funeral, 1889 December 31.
    - Manuscripts and agreements, 1858-1890; 2 (Box 16)
      The Lord's Prayer, written within the compass of half a crown, and the Lord's Prayer in English and French within the compass of a threepenny piece. Accompanied by a printed copy.
      Entry of marriage for Sala and Bessie Stannard, certified copy, 1890 January 25. 1 page.
      Financial accounts for Homburg tour, 1858 November. 1 page.
      "Welcome Guest," note and sketch, 1859 January. 1 page.
      The Seven Sons of Mammon: agreement with Edward Tinsley, 1861 October 9. 1 page.
      IOU to Charles Dickens and W. H. Wills, 1863 November 13. 1 page.
      My Diary in America in the Midst of War: agreement with Edward Tinsley, 1864 December 9. 1 page.
      Passport issued to Harriette Sala, 1865 November 22. 1 page.
      Printed calling card with address in Sala's hand, undated. 1 page.
      Postcard with clipping addressed in Sala's hand to Charles Dickens, 1870 December 6.
      Photograph of Sala, inscribed to Charles Godfrey Leland, 1874 March.
      Photograph of Sala, inscribed to Mr. and Mrs. Charles Skirrow, 1880 June.
      Inscription from a book, 1881 December. 1 page.
      Journal des Modes, 1876 February, signed, 1883 February 1883. 1 page.
      Menu, autograph manuscript, 1883 December 25. 1 page.
      Menu, autograph manuscript, 1884 August 11. 1 page.
      Photograph of Spanish gendarmes, with notes.
      Label from a scrapbook.
      2 autographs, clipped from documents.
  - Other Papers of Ralph Straus
    - Bibliography of George Augustus Henry Sala: I, 1942; 2 (Box 16)
    - Bibliography of George Augustus Henry Sala: II, undated; 3 (Box 16)
      Includes typed and manuscript bibliographical notes, rubbings, title pages, and pieces of binding material.
    - Correspondence, 1931-1935; 8 (Box 17)
      Incoming autograph letters, signed, to Straus, concerning his biography of Sala.
      Includes:
      Heal, Ambrose, 1931 December 12.
      Hird, Frank, 1935 July 29.
      Johnson, Charles Plumptre, 935 August 19.
      Lucas, E. V. (Edward Verrall), 1933 January 23.
      Mottram, R. H. (Ralph Hale), 1933. Accompanied by letter from Fred Sidney Davis to R. H. Mottram, 1933 August 10.
      Richardson, Joseph Hall, 1934 January 9.
      Wright, Thomas, 1935 December 7.
    - Handlist of publications, undated; 2 (Box 17)
      List of Sala's publications, illustrations, theatrical productions, periodical contributions and public addresses. Contains a chronological listing of Sala's works published in periodicals, and an index to these periodicals.
    - The homes of Sala. Clippings and prints, 1848-1895; 2 (Box 17)
    - The library of George Augustus Sala. Typescript, 1845-1895; 5 (Box 18)
      List of books owned by George Augustus Sala, in order of acquisition, with transcriptions of inscriptions and other notes by Sala.
      With 2 letters and 2 postcards from booksellers to Straus about books owned by Sala.
    - "A Man With a Nose" and other writings by Straus about Sala, 1933-1934 (Box 18)
    - Material for the life of George Augustus Henry Sala, 1828-1854; 2 (Box 18)
    - Material for the life of George Augustus Henry Sala, 1855-1862; 4 (Box 18)
    - Material for the life of George Augustus Henry Sala, 1863-1869; 3 (Box 19)
    - Material for the life of George Augustus Henry Sala, 1870-1876; 3 (Box 19)
    - Material for the life of George Augustus Henry Sala, 1877-1883; 3 (Box 19)
    - Material for the life of George Augustus Henry Sala, 1884-1890; 3 (Box 19)
    - Material for the life of George Augustus Henry Sala, 1891-1941; 5 (Box 20)
    - Notebook, 1851-1895 (Box 20)
      Daily listing of writings and activities of Sala
    - Photographs, engravings, etc., undated; 3 (Box 21)
    - Portraits and caricatures of George Augustus Sala, 1836-1879; 6 (Box 21)
    - Portraits and caricatures of George Augustus Sala, 1880-1887; 7 (Box 22)
    - Portraits and caricatures of George Augustus Sala, 1888-1895 (Box 22)
    - Portraits and caricatures of George Augustus Sala, 1888-1895; 5 (Box 23)
    - Punch and Sala: clippings, 1863-1895; 3 (Box 23)
    - Sala in the law courts: legal cases: clippings, 1860-1895; 2 (Box 23)
    - Sala: the Portrait of an Eminent Victorian, undated (Box 23)
      Fragment, autograph manuscript, pages 257-259.
    - Scraps, undated; 7 (Box 24)
      Contains clippings of pictures of Sala and contemporary people and places; articles by Sala; fragments of proofs for Straus's Sala: the Portrait of an Eminent Victorian; and manuscript notes by Straus.
- Materials from Other Sources, 1855-1899; Series II; 0.42; (1 box)
  Organized into two subseries: Correspondence, arranged alphabetically by name; and Other Papers, arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  Correspondence consists of autograph letters, signed, from Sala, with a few third-party letters from J. Hain Friswell. Other Papers contains writings and notes by Sala, most autograph manuscript.
  - Correspondence
    Outgoing autograph letters, signed, from Sala, unless otherwise noted.
    - Barrett, Lawrence, 1884 May 22 (Box 26 (Oversize))
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      Purchased From David J. Holmes on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1997.
      Mounted on album leaf, with 8 clippings. Accompanied by 3 clippings, and manuscript notes in an unidentified hand.
    - Behan, L. T., 1865 March 31 (Box 25)
      Gift of Robert F. Metzdorf, 1958.
    - Byron, H. J. (Henry James), 1877 September 28 (Box 25)
      Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 2002.
      Accompanied by "The ruined man of Monaco," fragment, autograph manuscript.
    - Cassell, Petter & Galpin, [1869] April 20 (Box 25)
      Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1995.
    - Chapman, T., undated (Box 25)
      Purchased from Clive Farahar and Sophie Dupre on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1998.
    - Clarke, Campbell, Mr. and Mrs., 1877-1895 (Box 25)
      Purchased from John Schroder on the William Lyon Phelps Memorial Fund, 1955.
      17 letters.
    - Cridland, J., undated (Box 25)
      Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Walter Jennings Memorial Fund, 1996.
      2 letters.
    - De La Pryme, Charles, no year March 7 (Box 25)
      Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1999.
    - Dixon, William Hepworth, 1865 March 6 (Box 25)
      Purchased from Maggs Brothers on the William Lyon Phelps Memorial Fund, 1956.
      Accompanied by clippings.
    - Eykyn, Robert, 1884 November 6 (Box 25)
      Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1997.
    - Friswell, J. Hain (James Hain), 1871 January 2 (Box 25)
      Purchased from Pickering and Chatto on the Plain Fund, 1946.
      From Friswell to H. P. Robinson, about Sala.
      Removed from Friswell, J. Hain. Modern Men of Letters Honestly Criticised (London, 1870).
    - Friswell, J. Hain (James Hain), 1871 March 11 (Box 25)
      From Friswell to John D. Ford about Sala.
    - George Routledge and Sons, 1873 May 22 (Box 25)
      Purchased from an unknown source on the Francis O. Matthiesen Fund, 1957.
    - Helps, Arthur, 1860, 1874 (Box 25)
      Purchased from C. A. Stonehill on the Frank Altschul Fund, 1962.
    - Illustrated London News, undated (Box 25)
      Fragment of an envelope.
    - Johnson, Monsieur, 1889 March 12 (Box 25)
      Purchased from Clive Farahar and Sophie Dupre on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 1998.
      In French, with a typescript English translation.
    - Leland, Charles Godfrey, 1874, 1876 (Box 25)
      Purchased from Maggs Brothers on the Plain Fund, 1954.
    - Paist, J. H., 1879 December 4 (Box 25)
    - Payne, J. Bertrand (James Bertrand), undated (Box 25)
      With letter to Cornelius Walford, 1883 April 12, with draft of letter to an unidentified recipient on verso, 1883 March 15.
    - Reid, T. Wemyss (Thomas Wemyss), undated (Box 25)
    - Richardson, H. F., 1883 March 20, undated (Box 25)
      Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2005.
      Accompanied by engraved portrait of Sala and 1 clipping.
    - Russell, W. H., Dr., 1893 March 12 (Box 25)
      Purchased from J. F. Fleming on the William Lyon Phelps Memorial Fund, 1956.
    - Skirrow, Charles, [1878] (Box 25)
      Gift of Walter Goldwater, 1958.
    - Smith, George, [1860] (Box 25)
      Purchased from Michael Silverman on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 2005.
    - Thomas, Annie, 1876-1878 (Box 25)
      4 letters
      Accompanied by letter from Sala to W. J. Smith, 1892 January 25; and letter from Henrietta Catherina Florentina Simon Sala to "Mr. Smith," 1836 December 21.
    - Thomas, F. Moy, 1891 September 22 (Box 25)
    - Thornbury, Walter, undated (Box 25)
    - Tinsley, William, circa 1866 (Box 25)
      Purchase from Maggs Brothers on the Plain Fund, 1954.
    - Tinsley, William, 1875 April 10 (Box 25)
      Gift of James Hosmer Penniman, date unknown.
    - Tinsley, William, [1896?] (Box 25)
      Accompanied by engraved portrait of Sala.
    - Toole, John Lawrence, 1884 (Box 25)
    - Tyler, W., 1862 January (Box 25)
      Accompanied by a clipping.
    - Vizetelly, Henry, 1874 May 28 (Box 25)
    - Williams, Charles, 1870 April 12 (Box 25)
      Purchased from I. K. Fletcher on the Henry Homes Fund, 1957.
    - Other letters, 1872-1884 (Box 25)
      Gift of Arthur Pforzheimer, 1937.
      Contains letters from Sala to:
      Gallenga, Antonio Carlo Napoleone, 1871 February 20.
      Mayhew, Augustus, 1872 July 1.
      Mellison, John, 1876 July 10.
      "Bethune, Mr.," 1879 July 7.
      Lupton, I. T., 1882 July 13.
      Downing, William, 1883 January 25.
      Bromhead, V. G., appended to an unidentified fragment, autograph manuscript, 1883 December 8.
      Skirrow, Charles, Mrs., with drawing, pen-and-ink and watercolor, 1884 April 19.
      Hallett, Hughes, 1884 October 19 and 1887 March 7.
      Cole, Henry, Hotel, undated.
      Dusser, Christopher, undated.
    - Letters to George Augustus Sala, 1874-1899 (Box 25)
      Purchased from Fletcher on the Plain Fund, 1954.
      7 letters.
    - Unidentified, 1871 November 18 (Box 25)
      To "My dear Huntington."
    - Unidentified, 1855 July 26 (Box 25)
      To "Sir."
      Accompanied by Sala's Journal, 1892, April 20.
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 25)
      Purchased from Clive Farahar & Sophie Dupre on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1998.
      Fragment, with signature.
  - Other Papers
    - "The Prophet Isaiah on North and South, Liverpool," autograph manuscript, no year October 13 (Box 25)
      Purchased from John Schroder on the Plain Fund, 1954.
    - "The Strange Behaviour of Mr. Apostolo," page proofs, corrected, undated (Box 25)
      Gift of Charles A. Stonehill, 1947.
      Published in Belgravia Annual, 1877.
    - Summons from Queen's Bench Court, 1870 January 20 (Box 25)
      Purchased from R. F. Metzdorf on the Francis O. Matthiesen Fund, 1957.
      With endorsement on verso, 10 July 1869.
    - Notes, autograph manuscript, 1880 October 7 (Box 25)
      Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 2003.
      With appended note to Major General Faulkner.
    - Album inscription, autograph manuscript, 1877-1887 (Box 25)
      With autograph manuscript inscriptions by William Black, 1887 October; and Max O'Rell, 1887 January 10.